Even the IMF is now getting nervous.
Nervous to the point that its chief
economist today said, "We're drifting
closer to their newly minted adverse
scenario." What does that mean? It means
we're getting closer and closer to that
point of no return. They might be a lot
closer than people expect because of how
fragile the situation is, that we were
not in a good place to start before we
got to the energy shock. And the
difference between fragile and resilient
makes all the difference when it comes
to that collision course. Now, what the
IMF guy actually said was, quote, "I
would say that we are somewhere in
between the reference scenario and the
adverse scenario. And of course, every
day that passes and every day that we
have more disruption in energy, we are
drifting closer towards the adverse
scenario. We are, as I keep saying, in a
race against time. And it's not against
oil inflation, it's oil recession.
Energy shocks are inherently
contractionary, not inflationary. That
was true in the '70s, contrary to all
the myths that are floating around on X
and YouTube and elsewhere. We saw it in
1990 and again in 2008. Even the dot-com
recession, right at the start of the
2000s, was to some extent provoked by a
sharp increase in energy costs from the
late 20th century. So, the question
isn't necessarily how high oil prices
will go or just how long they'll stay
there. It's a combination of those plus
fragility. That's the key ingredient
that everyone either leaves out or they
get completely wrong.
There was this narrative that the
economy worldwide was either in a good
place or was heading toward one. Of
course, Christine Lagarde couldn't stop
saying that phrase over and over and
over again. But that wasn't true. And
what we're seeing in the evidence, even
before we got to the energy shock, was
it wasn't about tariffs in 2025,
therefore recovery in 2026. It's a
downturn that began in 2024, which means
a much more fragile situation before we
get to the energy shock, therefore a
lower threshold for that point of no
return. That point between where we are
today and the adverse and maybe even
severe scenarios.
So, let's start with what the IMF
reported in its April 2026 update to its
World Economic Outlook. Quote, "The
International Monetary Fund cut its
growth outlook on Tuesday due to Hormuz
Strait war-driven energy price spikes,
but said the world was already drifting
toward a more adverse scenario with much
weaker growth as the Strait of Hormuz
shipping disruptions continue. Under the
IMF's worst-case outlook, the global
economy teeters on the brink of
recession, actually goes over into
recession, with oil prices averaging
$110 a barrel in 2026 and $125 in 2027."
And that's the point which I'll get to a
little bit later on. need to be that
high or that long. Just minutes after
releasing the outlook, IMF chief
economist Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas said
it may already be outdated. He told
reporters that with continued energy
disruptions and no clear path to end the
conflict, the IMF's adverse scenario
looks increasingly likely. Now, the
problem now, as far as oil is concerned,
is that there's a lot of catching up to
do. The Strait of Hormuz has been
effectively closed for 6 weeks. And that
has drained supplies of petroleum and
downstream products. And this is, I keep
putting out this, too. People don't
appreciate this is a historic disruption
amounting to almost 20%
of global daily usage. Now, workarounds
have been able to claw back some of that
gap, but they're being increasingly
stressed to and some of them, like
inventories, they're finite and coming
up against their limits. And contrary to
the IMF's seemingly singular focus on
oil prices, the lack of physical supply
is becoming a significant problem in and
of itself. And I'll give you an example
of where the downstream effects
they're already beginning to show up in
the real economy. Quote, "Virgin
Australia has followed in Qantas'
footsteps by cutting flights, hiking
airfares, and warning of increased fuel
costs due to the oil crisis. The airline
on Wednesday told customers and
investors that it was forced to make
changes as customer demand remained
strong and fuel costs were elevated.
Virgin said its capacity was reducing by
1% in the 3 months to June 30th and was
hiking fares to offset the impact of
reduced capacity and heightened fuel
costs. Now, the national carrier,
they're talking about Qantas, also told
customers and investors that it and
Jetstar's domestic operations will
reduce by 5%
in the 3 months to June 30th. The
carrier also warned that jet fuel
refining costs have risen from $20 per
barrel to $120 per barrel." Again, the
oil shock is much bigger than people
uh realize at this moment. Before we go
on with our video today, let me ask you
a question. What if your gold could
actually pay you every single month in
more gold? That's what today's video
sponsor, Monetary Metals, lets you do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold, it's still in your name, it's
fully insured, but instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
starts working for you. Monetary Metals
has built a system that turns idle gold
into productive gold, earning real yield
paid in physical gold, not dollars. No
selling, no trading, no converting. You
keep your gold and every month you get
more of it. It's a simple idea, but it
solves a big problem. If gold is money,
it should act like money. And now it
finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, but now let's get
back to the rest of our video.
In other words,
we're already drifting into that adverse
scenario, the one that is consistent
with how past oil shocks have played
out. They are not inflationary apart
from a short-run increase in consumer
price rates. They're not inflationary.
So, the CPI rate goes up for a couple
months, then it comes right back down
after enough activity gets choked off.
And it doesn't take a whole lot of time
for this to happen. Now, the IMF is
assuming oil prices stay up in the '90s
under their adverse scenario for maybe
the rest of the year. And then at $100
and more, as we said before, for the
severe path. But for the adverse
scenario, they have world GDP dropping
to just 2.5% growth from over 3%. Now,
the severe shock pushes the rate down to
2% flat. And these may not sound like
big changes, but historically, whenever
global real GDP growth is around 2% or
even less, the entire world economy is
experiencing a full-blown, NBER will
call it, recession. And as the economy
strains under persistently higher oil
prices, the more the shock will resemble
those past historical examples, which
uniformly are not inflationary. And they
don't need to go as high or stay as high
when the economy is more fragile to
start with. Now, even the oil shocks in
the 1970s weren't inflationary. That's a
huge misconception. People have this
idea that OPEC's embargo in late '73
caused the great inflation. Not even
close. In fact, by October '73, the
great inflation itself was already
seven, maybe eight years old by then,
depending upon where you mark the start
of it, you know, late '65 or early '66.
That's the part you never hear. People
are running around social media as if
the great inflation just showed up in
late 1973 with OPEC. No. The actual
monetary expansion, the eurodollar
expansion, goes way back much earlier
than all that. And that's the inflation.
Oil prices just added a little bit to it
before subtracting from it. By 1973, the
great inflation was already well
entrenched and it was accelerating. When
the oil shock hit, it did add to
consumer prices and pump up consumer
price rates, but only temporarily.
The CPI had shot up from 3.5% year over
year at the start of '73 to nearly 7.5%
throughout that year before the embargo.
Then with higher oil, it kept going to
12% in later '74, which is why people
get this idea, before eventually
dropping off with economic activity, the
recession, the steep rise in
unemployment that it provoked, which
knocked the CPI rate back down below 7%
by the end of 1975. Oil did not create
the inflation. The eurodollar expansion
did, and it did so years before. So,
OPEC merely added something to the price
effect, which then caused businesses to
cut back on employment costs, therefore
consumers on spending. Unemployment rose
and the oil shock overall helped plunge
the US and global economy into
recession, which temporarily halted the
great inflation's advance. Since it
wasn't really about oil, the inflation
acceleration came roaring back in the
second half of the decade without
another oil shock, though. There would
be another one later in 1979 to finish
off another business cycle by 1980. So,
even in the '70s, the oil shock didn't
create inflation. It temporarily raised
prices and price rates before the strain
on activity and finances eventually led
to contraction in both via higher
joblessness. Even the IMF's poor
econometric models are picking up on
this historical template because in the
end of the day, it's basic economic
arithmetic. A shock means oil prices are
being forced higher for non-economic
reasons, therefore crude isn't being
driven by rising incomes and demand.
that income growth, the higher energy
costs force consumers to cut back in
other kinds of spending, largely
discretionary items like we've talked
about before with vacations and eating
out. While businesses are stuck having
to cut other costs, leading them to
reduce employment expenses. Unemployment
goes up. They trim even more hours and
if the shock goes on long enough, they
really do start laying off workers. How
much time the economy has depends, as I
said, on several factors, starting with
its initial condition. How strong or
actually fragile a system might be
before the shock shows up. And this is
where the IMS data, their fairly lengthy
database, really helps establish that
background, both the short-run picture
as well as the longer term because
there was this idea, prevalent idea,
that the the weakness in 2025, the
joblessness that showed up in the
establishment survey, was all about
tariffs and tariff uncertainty.
Therefore, once the entire world
normalized to trade wars, it could move
on into recovery in 2026. Things were
good and heading into the right
direction here this year. And this idea
of a pickup got to be so entrenched at
the end of last year, the media got to
be filled with all these stories touting
the end of the Pringle cycle. The rate
cutting was over. They all said the same
thing. Even some officials got into the
act. The ECB, several people there were
talking about maybe how its next move in
2026 was going to be a rate hike. And
this was months before Iran.
But that mini hawkish wave didn't last
all that long. By early January, it was
starting to become clear enough, at
least to those paying attention, there
was no pickup. The true reason why was
that it had never been tariffs to begin
with. They were wrong in believing, for
example, US job losses in the spring and
summer 2025, then the fall and the
winter, that is those were all about
tariffs. And that consumer pessimism,
that had been an overreaction to trade
wars. No, consumers were saying all
along they were seeing worsening
fundamentals at their workplaces.
Therefore, they were increasingly
pessimistic about employment prospects,
jobs, and incomes, which the data shows
they were correct to be worried about
because they had already taken a long
dark turn before trade wars, months
before even Donald Trump was reelected
back in 2024. We see it all across the
data, especially now in the one series
most people pay attention to, the
payroll report, that they've been
revised to better reflect the ground
reality that consumers were well aware
of and trying to warn us about long
before economists, central bankers, and
the financial media finally figured this
out. It wasn't tariffs. Therefore,
getting used to tariffs wasn't going to
magically end the downturn, which
predated tariffs. Let me give you
another example. Again, let's go back to
the labor market. Fragility and
deterioration long before trade wars,
and they lasted well after the system
had normalized to them. We're going to
go up to Canada because Canadian
payrolls began to decline, like a lot of
the world, around March 2024. The same
global pivot, which shows up all over
the place. And why? Because it was in
the aftermath of a mini oil shock,
fragile circumstances, that were
provoked by non-economic geopolitics. In
that case, it was the combination of
OPEC production cuts and Yemeni rebels.
So, job growth in Canada back in 2024
began to disappear. The unemployment
rate really started to pick up, and even
the participation rate slid sharply as
Canadian workers started to drop out of
the labor force. And this should sound
very familiar, globally synchronized.
Now, there was a short-run jump in
employment at the end of 2024, but that
was actually
if there was a main tariff effect, that
was it, the artificial high that we
talked about from the very beginning.
Canadian producers were rushing to get
everything done before the tariff rates
did go into effect. And of course, at
the time, the Bank of Canada and its
officials ridiculously tried to take
credit for that short-run bump, claiming
it was the good work of their previous
rate cuts. But then, job cuts started to
hit really in the middle of 2025 before,
once again, later last year, another
tariff-induced distortion, the same one
that helped drive this idea that it was
really all about tariffs, the weakness
was over, and that Canada's economy had
begun to recover. Except, it didn't.
Job growth instead stalled in December
before dropping in January and then
crashing in February, shocking
everybody. This is supposed to be the
year of pickup, and instead, payrolls
crash in February, which is even before
the oil shock. And then March payrolls,
while they came in positive, they were
barely positive and nowhere near enough
to offset the previous contraction. So,
the same flat beverage downturn as
before, the same one that showed up 2
years ago back in early 2024, and all of
that prior to the energy shock. Fragile,
not resilient. And to further emphasize
that point, as well as the big picture
background, let's go back to the IMF
data because it really shows, it really
drives home this point. The economy is
not resilient. It has been struggling
for a lot longer than most people
realize because all you hear about is
the last GDP report, the last payroll
number, especially when it's positive.
You never hear about the complete
context.
The truth is, the global economy has
been way off trend ever since 2008. And
it shows. When you really look at it, it
shows. There's been no economic boom in
at least 20 years. Fragile. And you can
really see the deterioration in nominal
terms, and in trade, too, to where the
silent depression just pops right out of
the charts. The world completely changed
after '08, and it never got back on
track. The eurodollar broke, and it
broke trade, and without the money and
credit flows,
demand destruction flowed from monetary
destruction. So, trade volumes, look at
those. They've slipped so far away from
the prior eurodollar trend. No wonder
there's no growth in a lot of places,
particularly China. You want to know why
China is the way it is? Right here is
the explanation and the proof. Now,
contrary to what most people have been
told, the 2020s didn't change anything.
Well, they, you know, COVID and the
pandemic had the
kind of erased everybody's memories.
What really happened was the price shock
and aftermath of lockdowns only made
everything worse. Just look at nominal
GDP and the trend again. Despite all the
quote-unquote inflation, what people
called that for the supply shock, it did
nothing to put the world closer to its
pre-2008
existence. We all got poorer for an
economy still in its depression mode.
So, when you put that together with the
energy shock, the downturn from the last
couple years, no wonder the initial
reactions to the energy shock have been,
in a lot of cases, pretty extreme and
pretty eye-opening. US consumer
sentiment, for example, the University
of Michigan's data just crashed to a
record low. Yes, a record low for the
month of April. Consumers know they
can't afford a prolonged increase in
energy costs. They just can't. The
economy was not in a good place. It was
in a fragile state, in particular, the
labor market. It wasn't catastrophic.
This is not early 2009, but it is far
from good. There was no pickup late in
2025, so 2026 began on the wrong foot
even before we got to Iran in March. So,
the University of Michigan sentiment
number, as I said, crashed to a record
low here in April. Record low. That's
not really about $100 oil. It's
consumers realizing that in the fragile
economic state they're in, $100 oil will
begin to break things, particularly
employment. They know employers have
been struggling for years waiting for a
turnaround that didn't happen. That
won't happen. And now, increasingly,
can't happen. Now, I've already
mentioned before the the consumer survey
data from the Federal Reserve Bank of
New York, which shows no increase to
inflation expectations because consumers
realize what's going on here. But it did
point to a significant rise in the
number of Americans who say they're
worried about their financial situations
because they believe unemployment is
going to go up. At the same time, hiring
is all but gone extinct, especially in
this economy. And then, higher costs
just make a bad situation worse. The
latest survey on small businesses, the
NFIB, shows exactly the same thing from
the other side, on the employment side.
Quote, the
before we get to April, to 95.8,
according to figures released on
Tuesday. The survey, which was conducted
after the US and Israel launched the
Middle East conflict, indicated less
optimism about the outlook for earnings
and the economy. The net share of owners
who expect business conditions to
improve declined seven points to 11%,
the lowest since October 2024. And those
planning capital expenditures in the
next three to six months shrank to the
lowest since 2009.
And the uncertainty index climbed
higher. With capital expenditure plans
sinking,
so does employment plans because the
number of employers who are planning to
add to their staffs is stuck at at least
at last year's lows, down where it had
been during the so-called tariff
uncertainty months, the same ones, by
the way, when job shedding in the US
began to show up in more obvious ways.
So, how high do oil prices need to go,
and how long do they need to stay there
before what we're experiencing today
qualifies as an oil shock? Well, the
truth is,
we don't know. It's the kind of It's the
kind of thing you don't know until after
you go past it. You don't know you're
past the point of no return until you've
gone too far down that road.
What we can say is that the threshold
for that point is much lower when an
economy is in such a fragile state to
begin with. A truly resilient system is
one which can withstand multiple shots
and shocks, even big ones. Think about
the late 1990s in the US, and even
Europe, for that matter, following the
Asian not financial crisis in '97 and
'98, which was really just a dress
rehearsal for 2008. It produced a
significant dent, a significant dent in
the global system, yet barely anyone in
North America noticed because the '90s
boom was a real one and the economy
truly had been resilient. Nowadays, they
just they just tossed those words around
and just kind of hope that they stick.
But, here in 2026, we're drifting toward
an adverse scenario, which might be the
best phrase ever uttered by an IMF
official because they're both picking up
on the fragility and the oil shock
already. The initial initial response to
it, as well as finally figuring out
what's really happening. As I've been
saying, the world really is in a race
against time. And the basic economic
math is so simple and straightforward,
even mainstream econometric models can
see it, too. We are on a collision
course, and that collision happens to be
much closer than you think because,
contrary to what Christine Lagarde had
kept saying last year, we were not in a
good place, and that makes all the
difference.
The one thing the IMF didn't even touch
was private credit, the bust that's
going on there. As I said in yesterday's
video, 2008 was about big banks, 2026 is
about big insurance. That's all in the
video link below. As always, thank you
very much for joining me. Huge thank you
Euro Dollar University members and
subscribers, and until next time,
take care.